Alright, so let's talk about the actual
exam content then.
What to expect on the exam.
The exam is a computer-based exam.
Let me start again.
The PMP exam is a computer-based exam,
right?
And you have the option choice of either
taking it at a testing center,
a Pearson View testing
center, or you can take it as
an online procted exam,
again procted by Pearson View.
And we have a separate video on discussing
the pros and cons of a of each option.
But because it's a computer-based exam,
you will get your results immediately.
Now, the exam is 180 questions.
There's 180 random multiple choice
questions in the exam.
Now, it's all multiple choice.
Sure, there's going
to be different formats,
which, again, we've
covered in a separate video.
But there's 180 random multiple choice
questions to do in 3 hours and 50 minutes.
or 230 minutes.
So 180 questions in 230
minutes basically means 76
seconds a question, a minute
and 16 seconds per question.
So you can see now, time management is
absolutely vital in an exam like this.
76 seconds does not give you a lot of time
in which to answer a question.
So that's why you need to practice,
right?
You really need to practice.
Now, when I say these are random questions,
they're random based on the syllabus.
So in other words, the
next question has got
nothing to do with the
question that you just did.
Questions don't follow on from one
another.
So you may be answering a question based
on the schedule.
The next question might be based on risk.
The question after that might be a
procurement question.
So there's no sections on the exam in that
way, in that respect.
all completely random.
Now PMI have a data bank of around 13,000
questions of which 180
are selected at random.
So you can see now no two exams are going
to be the same.
Everybody's exam is going to be different
and everybody will get a different set of
questions and a different exam experience
altogether.
Now the way the exam is actually
structured, it is you have three sections,
three random sections, right, of 60
questions each, right?
So three sections of 60 questions,
180, 180 questions.
And in between each section, there's a 10
minute break.
So you start the exam and you first answer
the first set of 60 questions.
During those set of 60 questions,
you can skip questions, come back to them,
Mark them for review, come back to them
later, change your answer, you know,
however you want to.
You can just go back and forth.
After those 60 questions are complete,
right?
Then again, you have the
option of going back, changing
your answer if you want,
right, reviewing them.
Now, then you start your break.
There's a break.
There's a 10-minute break.
As soon as that break
starts, you have no access
to those previous 60
questions that you just did.
Now, this is a 10-minute break,
but you have an option.
You don't have to take the full 10
minutes.
but that's a maximum you can take.
You can take a portion of it.
You can just take a couple of minutes if
you want, or you don't
have to take a break.
Then you start the next set of 60
questions.
And again, the same thing.
So you have three sections then.
And that's all the more reason why time
management is even more important.
If you spend too long in the first
section, then that's going to eat into
your second section, which is then going
to eat into your third section.
In which case, then, you might not have
enough time to finish the exam.
So you have to be very, very careful.
Now, there are five experimental
questions.
That doesn't really concern you too much.
It really doesn't concern you guys too
much.
The actual exam is actually marked out of
175 questions.
These experimental questions are just
really for PMI's purposes.
When they're submitting questions,
they're seeing how students are answering.
those questions right before they actually
determine whether it's an actual PMP exam
question or whether they need to modify it
or whatever.
So the problem is you don't know what
those experimental questions are,
they're all mixed in,
and also you don't get
any credit for those
experimental questions.
You could get all five of them correct or
all five of them incorrect, it makes no
difference to your score because the
actual exam is marked out of 175 questions.
Although I said it's a random exam,
it is a random exam, completely random,
but it's based on these parameters here.
So you have the three domains.
You have the process domain, the people
domain, the business environment domain,
right?
These are the three
domains that make up, you
know, PMI's principles
or project management.
So the way the exam is broken up is 50% of
the exam is from the process domain,
42% of the exam from the people domain.
8% of the exam is a business environment
domain.
All the exams, that's how they are broken
up.
So they're all random based on these
parameters here.
But again, it's all mixed up.
So in the first section, you will have
questions from all three of these domains,
all the knowledge areas.
In the second section, the second 60
question section, Again, they'll have
questions from all of
the different domains,
knowledge areas, and so on and so forth.
Now, the actual results, right,
so when you get your exam results,
I said, you get it immediately,
you just got a pass or fail.
They don't give you a score.
They don't give you a grade.
It's just a pass or fail.
But what the other
information they give you
is, for each of the
domains, they tell you.
are you above target, on target,
below target, or needs improvement?
And essentially, if you're above target or
target, you will pass.
If you're below target or needs
improvement, you'll fail.
Now, one very common question that people
have is, well, what's
the actual pass Mark?
And the very simple answer is,
literally, we don't know.
It's unknown.
There is no set pass Mark for the PNP
exam.
The pass Mark is dependent on the actual
exam that you get.
Remember, the exam can vary a lot.
There's 13,000 questions of which 180 are
going to be selected at random.
So there's a lot of variation on the exam.
Some people get a really easy exam.
Some people get really tough exam.
If you end up with a really
easy exam, your pass marks
going to be a lot higher than
if you get a real tough exam.
So there is some kind of weighting on the
exam.
Now, what the exact waiting is,
what the exact range is, we don't know.
PMI never released that information.
They're very secretive about that kind of
information.
So the general pointer that we will give
you is, as you're taking practice exams,
right, make sure you're aiming to score in
the 70, right, upper 70, 80%, right?
When you're consistently
around that range, then you can
feel comfortable that you're
ready for the real exam.
Now, just a little exam tip here.
don't be hung up, don't
get stressed if you see
the first few questions
to be really difficult.
It's very, very common to
have the first few questions, the
first 10, 15 questions to be the
hardest questions on the exam.
Don't start panicking if that happens to
you.
If you start, if you can't answer the
first few questions, no big deal,
just skip, skip, skip,
go to the next question,
go to the next question.
until you get to a question that you can
answer.
If you start panicking right at the
beginning, then that can see your fate.
Just the first couple of
minutes could determine
whether or not you're going
to pass or fail the exam.
So if you can't answer the first few
questions, just keep your composure.
I know it's easier said than done,
but just keep your composure.
Just click next, next, next, until you get
your question that you can't answer.
This is a tough.
exam but don't stress right there's no
reason to stress either